Guide to the Ford E. and Harriet R. Curtis Theatre Collection of Pennsylvania Theatre Programs, 1870-present CTC.1966.04
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Ford E. and Harriet R. Curtis Theatre Collection of Pennsylvania Theatre Programs
1870-present
CTC.1966.04
ULS Archives & Special Collections
6.0 linear feet (14 mss boxes)
The Ford E. and Harriet R. Curtis Theatre Collection consists of Pennsylvania theatre programs from the 1870's to the present. In some instances, newspaper clippings, marketing materials, photographs, and memorabilia related to the theatres and performing arts companies are stored with the programs.
Curtis, Ford E., 1896-1979
Curtis, Harriet R., d. 1971
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
History
The Ford E. and Harriet R. Curtis Theatre Collection includes theatre programs collected by Dr. Ford E. Curtis and his wife, Harriet. Dr. Curtis began teaching drama in the English department at the University of Pittsburgh in 1924. He and his wife were avid theatre goers, attending performances every week. After his retirement in 1961, he began to add to their personal collection of playbills and programs in the hopes of building a collection to donate to Pitt.
The materials that Dr. Curtis amassed included his own collection and materials donated to him. In addition to Dr. Curtis' donation to the University of Pittsburgh, the Curtis Collection staff still acquires additional programs to add to this collection and help to document the history of theatre and the performing arts in Pittsburgh and western Pennsylvania.
Scope and Content Notes
This collection is separated into three series: Pennsylvania, Philadelphia, and the Theatre Association of Pennsylvania.
Individual programs in the Pennsylvania series are mostly organized by the theatre or venue where the production took place. These venues are arranged alphabetically by name, then chronologically. With each venue or group, the total number of document folders is listed. The folders are not numbered consecutively as found in other archival collections because these numbers regularly change with new donations. Typically, the collection's policy is to only keep two copies of a program, although exceptions to this include commemorative programs and programs that are autographed or contain marginalia.
The Philadelphia series of this collection are arranged chronologically by the year of the performance. The bulk of the programs are from 1950-1970. The same program collecting policies described above apply to the Philadelphia programs as well.
Please note that there is a separate collection guide for Pittsburgh theatre programs, see the related material section below.
Arrangement
This collection is divided into three series:
I. Pennsylvania Programs, 1877-
II. Philadelphia Programs, 1870-
III. Theatre Association of Pennsylvania, 1974-1990
Accruals
Donations are occasionally added to the collection; many of these donations come from the general public. If you are interested in donating theatre programs to the collection, please contact the Special Collections Department.
Previous Citation
Ford E. and Harriet R. Curtis Theatre Collection of Pennsylvania Theatre Programs, 1870-present, CTC.1966.04, Curtis Theatre Collection, Special Collections Department, University of Pittsburgh
Related Material
Ford E. and Harriet R. Curtis Theatre Collection of Pittsburgh Theatre Programs, 1840-present, Curtis Theatre Collection, Archives & Special Collections Department, University of Pittsburgh Library System
Michael Ellis Papers, 1937-1985, CTC.1977.02, Curtis Theatre Collection, Archives & Special Collections Department, University of Pittsburgh Library System
Academy of Music (Scranton, Pa.).; Berks Summer Theater (Program: Reading, Pa.).; Bloombsburg Theatre Ensemble (Bloomsburg, Pa.).; Broad Street Theatre (Philadelphia, Pa.).; Bucks County Playhouse (Organization).; Chestnut Street Opera House (Philadelphia, Pa.).; Chestnut Street Theatre (Philadelphia, Pa.).; Erlanger Theatre (Organization: Philadelphia, Pa.).; Forrest Theatre (Organization: Philadelphia, Pa.).; Fulton Opera House.; Garrick Theatre (Organization: Philadelphia, Pa.).; Grand Opera House (Philadelphia, Pa.).; Hedgerow Theatre (Organization: Rose Valley, Pa.).; Independent Eye.; Lyric Theatre (Organization: Philadelphia, Pa.).; Metropolitan Opera House (Organization: Philadelphia, Pa.).; Orpheum Theatre (Philadelphia, Pa.).; People's Light & Theatre Company.; Pocono Playhouse (Organization: Mountainhome, Pa.).; Shubert Theatre (Organization: Philadelphia, Pa.).; Swarthmore Chautauqua Association.; Tamiment Playhouse.; Theatre Association of Pennsylvania.; Theatre of the Living Arts (Organization: Philadelphia, Pa.).; Valley Forge Music Fair (Organization: Devon, Pa.).; Walnut Street Theatre (Philadelphia, Pa.).; Performing arts -- Pennsylvania; Performing arts -- Pennsylvania -- Bucks County; Theater -- Pennsylvania; Theater -- Pennsylvania -- Bucks County; Theater -- Pennsylvania -- Philadelphia; Theater -- Pennsylvania -- Philadelphia -- History -- 19th century
- Pennsylvania, 1877-; I.
  Scope and Content Notes
  The Pennsylvania series of this collection is arranged alphabetically by the title of the venue or performing arts group. Much of the Bucks County Playhouse materials were donated along with the Michael Ellis Papers.
  - Academy of Music - Scranton, 1878-1928; 1.0 folder
  - Actors Company of Pennsylvania - Lancaster, 1987; 1.0 folder
  - Allenberry Playhouse - Boiling Springs, 1959-1976; 6.0 folder
  - Allentown Society of Magicians - Northampton, 1963; 1.0 folder
  - Arena House - Harrisburg, 1965-1966; 1.0 folder
  - Arena Summer Theatre - State College, 1957; 1.0 folder
  - Bedford Springs Playhouse - Bedford, 1954-1966; 1.0 folder
  - Berks Players - Reading, 1955; 1.0 folder
  - Berwyn Playhouse - Berwyn, 1947-1949; 1.0 folder
  - Blaney Players - Wilkes-Barre, 1.0 folder
  - Bloomfield Civic Playhouse, 1948; 1.0 folder
  - Bloomsburg Theatre Ensemble - Bloomsburg, 1983; 1.0 folder
  - Bradford Summer Theatre - Bradford, 1950; 1.0 folder
  - Brandywine Music Circus - Concordville, 1958; 1.0 folder
  - Broadway Theatre League - Scranton, 1963-1989; 1.0 folder
  - Brookside Playhouse - Shamokin Dam, 1.0 folder
  - Brownsville Summer Playhouse - Brownsville, 1970; 1.0 folder
  - Buck Hill Players, 1946; 1.0 folder
  - Bucks County Playhouse - New Hope, 1939-1981; 3.0 box
  - Bushkill Playhouse - Bushkill, 1959; 1.0 folder
  - Business and Professional Women's Club - Columbia, 1964; 1.0 folder
  - By Hex Playhouse - Lancaster, 1964; 1.0 folder
  - Capitol Theatre - Reading, 1934-1945; 1.0 folder
  - Cherry Lane Playhouse - Tannersville, 1963-1964; 1.0 folder
  - Chestnut Street Theatre - Sunbury, 1919; 1.0 folder
  - Choral Hall - Sewickley, 1877; 1.0 folder
  - Civic Little Theatre - Allentown, 1947; 1.0 folder
  - Cobweb Theatre - Yardley, 1939-1951; 1.0 folder
  - Cochran Auditorium - Johnstown, 1971; 1.0 folder
  - Comerford Theatres - Scranton, 1.0 folder
  - Cresson Lake Playhouse - Spangler, 1974-1978; 1.0 folder
  - Dauphin County Folk Festival - Harrisburg, 1944; 1.0 folder
  - David Copperfield Theatre - Shawnee on Delaware, 1.0 folder
  - Deer Lake Theatre - Deer Lake, 1937-1950; 1.0 folder
  - Dixie Theatre - Uniontown, 1928; 1.0 folder
  - Drexel Hill Playhouse - Drexel Hill, 1.0 folder
  - Dutch Country Players - East Greenville, 1962; 1.0 folder
  - Ephrata Legion Star Playhouse - Ephrata, 1959-1961; 1.0 folder
  - Erie Philharmonic - Erie, 1986; 1.0 folder
  - Erie Playhouse - Erie, 1985-2000; 1.0 folder
  - Erie Theatre - Erie, 1938-1947; 1.0 folder
  - Footlight Players - Wayne, 1958-1962; 1.0 folder
  - Four Mile Creek Park Theatre - Erie, 1916; 1.0 folder
  - Fulton Opera House - Lancaster, 1917-1981; 1.0 folder
  - Gettysburg Civic Chorus - Gettysburg, 1978-1980; 1.0 folder
  - Gettysburg Summer Theatre - Gettysburg, 1963-1981; 4.0 folder
  - Gilded Cage Theatre - Lancaster, 1963; 1.0 folder
  - Globe Theater - Bethlehem, 1930; 1.0 folder
  - Grand Opera House - Wilkes-Barre, 1921; 1.0 folder
  - Grand Theatre - Reading, 1913; 1.0 folder
  - Green Gables Playhouse - Drums, 1939; 1.0 folder
  - Green Hills Playhouse - Reading, 1940-1961; 1.0 folder
  - Gretna Playhouse - Mt. Gretna, 1937-1997; 1.0 folder
  - Grove Theatre - Nuangola, 1938-1951; 2.0 folder
  - Guthsville Playhouse - Allentown, 1.0 folder
  - Hall Players - Harrisburg, 1915-1916; 1.0 folder
  - Hanover Community Players - Hanover, 1937-1958; 1.0 folder
  - Hanover Opera House - Hanover, 1919-1933; 1.0 folder
  - Harrisburg Community Theatre - Harrisburg, 1941-1956; 1.0 folder
  - Harvey's Lake Theatre - Alderson, 1.0 folder
  - Haubert Theatre - Newfoundland, 1939; 1.0 folder
  - Hayloft Theatre - Allentown, 1947-1950; 1.0 folder
  - Hedgerow Theatre - Moylan-Rose Valley, 1939-1964; 1.0 folder
  - Hellenic Youth Federation, 1.0 folder
  - Hershey Community Theatre - Hershey, 1930-1980; 1.0 folder
  - Hippodrome - Pottsville, 1.0 folder
  - Host Inn Theatre - Harrisburg, 1.0 folder
  - Independent Eye - Lancaster, 1988; 1.0 folder
  - Irving Theatre - Wilkes-Barre, 1926; 1.0 folder
  - Kenley Deer Lake Theatre - Deer Lake, 1947; 1.0 folder
  - Kenley Players - Lakewood, 1949-1950; 1.0 folder
  - Kenley Players - York, 1952; 1.0 folder
  - Keystone Repertory Theater - Indiana, 1998; 1.0 folder
  - Kilbuck Players - Kilbuck, 1936; 1.0 folder
  - King-Woodhull Summer Theatre - South Williamsport, 1946; 1.0 folder
  - Knickerbocker Summer Theatre - South Williamsport, 1947; 1.0 folder
  - Lakemont Theatre - Lakemont Landing, 1.0 folder
  - Lakewood Summer Playhouse - Barnesville, 1956-1958; 1.0 folder
  - Lambs Theatre - Pithole, 1964; 1.0 folder
  - Legion Star Playhouse - Ephrata, 1956-1970; 3.0 folder
  - Lewisburg Drama Club - Lewisburg, 1.0 folder
  - Little Theatre - Wilkes-Barre, 1933-1949; 1.0 folder
  - Lycoming County Playhouse - South Williamsport, 1946; 1.0 folder
  - Lyric Theatre - Allentown, 1905-1948; 1.0 folder
  - Lytle Opera House - Braddock, 1.0 folder
  - Majestic Theatre - Williamsport, 1915-1931; 1.0 folder
  - Mateer Playhouse - State College, 1960; 1.0 folder
  - Milford Theatre - Milford, 1946-1947; 1.0 folder
  - Mishler Theatre - Altoona, 1.0 folder
  - Neshaminy Valley Music Theater - Horsham, 1962; 1.0 folder
  - New Hope Academy of the Arts - New Hope, 1961; 1.0 folder
  - Olde Trail Playhouse - Richeyville, 1976; 1.0 folder
  - Orpheum - Esterly, 1.0 folder
  - Orpheum - York, 1924-1925; 1.0 folder
  - Orpheum Theatre - Easton, 1928; 1.0 folder
  - Paint Shop Theatre - Somerset, 1938; 1.0 folder
  - Park Opera House - Erie, 1.0 folder
  - Park Theatre - Hanover, 1931-1934; 1.0 folder
  - Penn Playhouse - Meadville, 1953; 1.0 folder
  - Pennsylvania Playhouse - Bethlehem, 1966; 1.0 folder
  - People's Light & Theatre Company, 1997-1999; 1.0 folder
  - Pine Grove Playhouse - Cambridge Springs, 1940-1941; 1.0 folder
  - Playhouse - Eagles Mere, 1947; 1.0 folder
  - Playhouse - Erie, 1932-1936; 1.0 folder
  - Playhouse - McConnellstown, 1.0 folder
  - Playhouse - Reading, 1964; 1.0 folder
  - Plaza Theatre - Reading, 1948; 1.0 folder
  - Pocono Playhouse - Mountainhome, 1949-1975; 1.0 folder
  - Poli's Theatre - Scranton, 1.0 folder
  - Public Auditorium - Erie, 1932; 1.0 folder
  - Quota Club - Lancaster, 1946; 1.0 folder
  - Riverside Inn Dinner Theatre - Riverside, 1.0 folder
  - Rolling Green Park Theatre - Sunbury, 1.0 folder
  - Shawnee Summer Theater - Shawnee on Delaware, 1935; 1.0 folder
  - Soisson Theatre - Connellsville, 1.0 folder
  - St. John Studio Theatre - Clearfield, 1978-1979; 1.0 folder
  - St. Matthew's Methodist Church - Valley Forge, 1962; 1.0 folder
  - Swarthmore Chautauqua Association - Swarthmore, 1.0 folder
  - Tamiment Playhouse - Tamiment, 1.0 folder
  - Temple Judea of Bucks County - Doyestown, 1967; 1.0 folder
  - Temple of Music - Conneaut Lake, 1.0 folder
  - Theatre Royal - York, 1951; 1.0 folder
  - Totem Pole Playhouse - Fayetteville, 1956-1981; 5.0 folder
  - Tracy Hall - Harrisburg, 1951; 1.0 folder
  - Trevose Summer Theatre - Trevose, 1950; 1.0 folder
  - Valley Forge Music Fair - Valley Forge, 1961-1968; 1.0 folder
  - Victory Players - Hanover, 1.0 folder
  - William Penn Auditorium - Harrisburg, 1940; 1.0 folder
  - Williamsport Summer Theatre - Williamsport, 1948; 1.0 folder
  - York Little Theatre - York, 1945; 1.0 folder
- Philadelphia, 1870-; II.
  The Philadelphia theatre programs are arranged chronologically by the year of the performance.
  - Programs, 1870-1909 (Box 1, Folder 1-25)
    This box also includes twelve folders of programs with no dates. They are arranged alphabetically by the play's title.
  - Programs, 1910-1925 (Box 2, Folder 1-14)
  - Programs, 1926-1929 (Box 3, Folder 1-4)
  - Programs, 1930-1949 (Box 4, Folder 1-14)
  - Programs, 1950-1963 (Box 5, Folder 1-12)
  - Programs, 1964- (Box 6, Folder 1-8)
- Theatre Association of Pennsylvania, 1974-1990; III.
  This series contains press releases, meeting minutes, by-laws and the constitution of the Theatre Association of Pennsylvania. The materials are organized chronologically.
  - Constitution and By-laws, April 1974; 1.0 folder (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Press Releases and Membership Information, 1978-1990 (Box 1, Folder 2-7)